Guide to the Halsey family papers, 1870-1975.
Halsey family papers, 1870-1975.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Halsey family papers, 1870-1975.
2966
Halsey family.
3.2 cubic ft.
Scrapbooks, notebooks, stock certificates, blueprints, articles, books, correspondence, photographs, pamphlets, manuscripts, a genealogy, and a painted portrait.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Personal and professional papers of Francis W. Halsey (Cornell University Class of 1873), a newspaper editor and writer, and of his brother, Frederick A. Halsey (Cornell University M.E. 1878), an engineer and author of a number of articles and books about engineering. Also, letters to Frederick Halsey's daughters Olga and Marion from Fred H. Colvin.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Francis Whiting Halsey (Cornell University Class of 1873) was born in Unadilla, New York on October 15, 1851, and was the son of Dr. Gaius L. Halsey, a prominent Civil War physician and surgeon. Francis Halsey held editorial positions with the Binghamton Times, the New York Tribune, and, from 1880-1922, the New York Times, where he established the Times Review of Books in 1896. He wrote or edited a number of books, including The Old New York Frontier, The Pioneers of Unadilla Village, The World's Famous Orations (with William Jennings Bryan), and The Best of the World's Classics (with Senator Henry Cabot Lodge). He was a trustee of the New York State Historical Association and the American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society, and a member of the American Historical Association, New York State Library Association, and Cornell University Club, of which he was president in 1882. In 1883 he married Virginia Isabel Forbes, who died in 1900.
Francis' brother, Frederick Arthur Halsey (Cornell University M.E. 1878), was an engineer and author of a number of articles and books about engineering, particularly concerning the metric system. He was for a time the editor of the American Machinist. Marion S. Halsey and Olga S. Halsey were Frederick A. Halsey's daughters.
Fred H. Colvin was a machinist, technical journalist, author, and editor. He authored or coauthored dozens of monographs, textbooks, and reference books on machining, and served as chief editor of the journal Machinery and co-editor of the journal American Machinist. He also published a book of poetry, Safety Valve, in 1952.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Scrapbooks of letters, clippings, pamphlets, and photographs relating to personal and professional activities of Francis W. Halsey; awards won by Francis W. and Frederick A. Halsey; Frederick A. Halsey's student notebooks, stock certificates, blueprints, published articles and books, typescript articles, and letters; and photographs, letters, and pamphlets concerning Olga Halsey, Marion S. Halsey, and Dr. Gaius Leonard Halsey. Also, a scrapbook compiled by Stella Spencer Halsey (Mrs. Frederick A.) and a Spencer family genealogy, as well as a volume evidently presented to Frederick A. Halsey in 1906 in appreciation of his work repairing clocks. Laid in the volume are notes and clippings relating to clock repairs.
Also, typewritten drafts and published versions of articles by Frederick A. Halsey, opposing the adoption of the metric system, including his article "The metric fallacy" in the Sibley Journal of Engineering (1931); a watercolor portrait of Frederick Halsey, dated 1935; portrait photographs of him, 1923 and circa 1935; poems written to him by his friends, circa 1909; and correspondence between Olga and Marion Halsey and Fred H. Colvin (1954-1965).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Halsey family.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Halsey, Francis Whiting, 1851-1919.; Halsey, Frederick A. (Frederick Arthur), 1856-1935.; Halsey, Gaius Leonard, 1819-1891.; Halsey, Marion S.; Halsey, Olga S., d. 1970.; Halsey, Stella Spencer.; Halsey, Virginia Isabel Forbes, d. 1900.; Colvin, Fred H. (Fred Herbert), 1867-1965.; American Historical Association.; American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society.; Cornell University Club.; New York State Historical Association.; New York State Library Association.
Titles:
American machinist.; Binghamton times.; New York tribune.; Times review of books.; New York times.
Subjects:
Engineering.; Journalism.; Medicine.; Metric system.; Authors.; Engineers.; Journalists.; Physicians.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care.; Unadilla (N.Y.).
Form and Genre Terms:
Blueprints.; Genealogies.; Photographs.; Watercolors (paintings)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Postcards (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Unpublished articles, 1924-1925, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Machinist, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Blueprints (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Premium Plan of Paying for Labor" (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Francis W. Halsey photos (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter to A. Halsey to Mr. Coon of Rand Drill Co., 1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lectures on History by Andrew D. White, Vol. I, notes of Francis W. Halsey, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Volume 1)
- Lectures on History by Andrew D. White, Vol. II, notes of Francis W. Halsey, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Volume 2)
- Lectures on History by Andrew D. White, Vol. III, notes of Francis W. Halsey, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Volume 3)
- Lectures on Ancient Roman History by W.C. Russell, notes of Francis W. Halsey, 1870 (Box 2, Volume 4)
- Notebook kept by Frederick A. Halsey: Notes on Physics, taken during the spring term of 1874, from the lectures of Prof. Anthony, Accoustics and Optics (Box 2, Volume 5)
- Notebook kept by Frederick A. Halsey: "Continuation of notes on Electricity and Magnetism, taken during the Winter and Spring terms of 1875, from the lectures of Pro. Anthony (Box 2, Volume 6)
- Volume (mimeo): A Course in Water Wheels, 1878. Published for the Senior Class in Civil Engineering at Cornell University, Ithaca, NY (Note by IL P, Church that he is indebted to Prof. E.A. Fuertes for the translation from Vol. II of J. Wrisback's Lehrbuch der Ingenieur Maschinemachanik.) (Box 2, Volume 7)
- Halsey, Frederick A. The Locomotive Link Motion. New York: Press of Locomotive Engineering, 1898 (Box 2, Volume 8)
- Halsey, Frederick A. Methods of Machine Shop Work. New York: McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1914 (Box 2, Volume 9)
- Halsey, Frederick A. The Metric Fallacy. 2nd ed. New York, 1919 (Box 2, Volume 10)
- Halsey, Frederick A. Slide Valve Gears. New York: D. Van Nostrand Co. (autographed), 1890 (Box 2, Volume 11)
- Halsey, Frederick A. Slide Valve Gears. Rev. New York: D. Van Nostrand Co., 1899 (Box 2, Volume 12)
- Halsey, Frederick A. The Use of the Slide Rule. Van Nostrand Science Series, No. 114. 3rd ed. New York, 1903 (Box 2, Volume 13)
- Worm and Spiral Greating. Van Nostrand Science Series, No. 116. New York, 1902 (Box 2, Volume 14)
- Smith, Charles F., Frederick A. Halsey and others. The Design and Construction of Cams. New York: Hill Publishing Co., 1906 (Box 2, Volume 15)
- News clippings re: the "reform movement" led by John DeWitt Warner and F.W.H. and to the "attacts" on the administration of Pres. White (Box 2, Volume 16)
- Scrapbook of F.A.H.: photos, letters, memos; Cornell, family, homes rooms (Box 2, Volume 17)
- Tennyson's 1832 Volume (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Faerie Queen (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Old French (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Rev. History 53 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Apollonius of Tyre (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Medieval French Literature (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Student Notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Drama in England II (Box 3, Folder 8)
- English Drama I (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Student Papers (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Students and Paper (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Coronement Loois (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Morte d'Arthur (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Newsclippings and articles on Metre System (Box 3, Folder 14)
- F.W.H.'s scrapbooks
  - Lectures, speeches, "Pioneers of Unadilla" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Old New York Frontier" (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - New York Times - Change to Appleton's (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - American Authors and Their Homes and Women Authors of Our Day in Their Homes (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Old New York Frontier (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Our Literary Deluge (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Loose pages from scrapbook (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Clippings (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Book Review items (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Francis W. Halsey to Olga Halsey, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Olga Halsey Incentive Award (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Olga Halsey Bureau of Employment Security (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Reno Marine Salvage System (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence Dr. Gaius Leonard Halsey to F.W.H., 1871-1889 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Frederick Halsey biography, etc. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Methods of Machine Shop Work, Halsey, McGraw-Hill Co. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- "Life of Francis W. Halsey" c 1972, c 1975 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Correspondence - photocopies (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Spencer family (Ithamer, b. 1733) (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Omnimeter (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Cornell Students' Handbook, 1912-1913 (Box 5)
- Volume evidently presented to Frederick A. Halsey in appreciation of his work repairing clocks, 1906 (Box 5)
- Leather watch-fob with medallion showing Ezra Cornell and date [MU-2042], 1865 (Box 5)
- 2 3/4" gold medal in case: "The American Society of Mechanical Engineers" [MU-2043], 1923 (Box 5)
- Fraternity key on gold chain with three ivory balls (watch fob) [MU-2044], 1886 (Box 5)
- Letters from Fred H. Colvin to Olga and Marion Halsey, 1954-1965 (Box 6)
- Typewritten manuscripts and letters by Frederick A. Halsey, and poems written to him by his friends, 1909-circa 1935 (Box 6)
- Printed article "The Metric Fallacy," Sibley Journal of Engineering, 1931 (Box 6)
- 2 portrait photographs and 1 watercolor portrait of Frederick Halsey, 1923-1935 (Box 6)